Arif Usta

Data Systems Group at University of Waterloo Waterloo, Ontario, Canada arifusta.github.io/ arif.usta@uwaterloo.ca

OBJECTIVE

Research scientist with 9 years of research experience in computer science. My research interests lie in the field of data management and search engines; specifically relating to the application of deep learning and nlp techniques for user friendly information retrieval interfaces.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Post-Doctoral Researcher

Sep 2021 - Present

Data Systems Group, University of Waterloo, ON, Canada

Supervisor: Prof. Semih Salihoglu

Research Area: Data Lakes.

Research Assistant

Sep 2015 - Aug 2021

Department of Computer Engineering, Bilkent University, Turkey

Supervisor: Prof. Ozgur Ulusoy

Research Area: Intelligent User Interfaces to Databases.

Research Intern Jun 2017 - Sep 2017

Data Management Group, Brown University, RI, US

• I was involved in a research conducted by Data Management Group in Brown University under supervision of Prof. Ugur Cetintemel. I contributed as an author to a research article published in SIGMOD'18.

EDUCATION

PhD, Computer Science

Sep 2015 - Aug 2021

Bilkent University, Turkey Supervisor: Prof. Ozgur Ulusov

Thesis: Towards deeply intelligent interfaces in relational databases

MS, Computer Science

Sep 2012 - Sep 2015

Bilkent University, Turkey

Thesis: Optimization of an Educational Search Engine Using Learning to Rank Algorithms

Supervisor: Prof. Ozgur Ulusov

Research Area: Information Retrieval, Search Engines

Tuition Fee Scholarship (%100)

Graduation GPA: 3.73

BS, Computer Science

Aug 2010 - Jan 2011

Uppsala University, Uppsala, Sweden

Erasmus Exchange Student

BS, Computer Science

Sep 2007 - June 2012

Bilkent University, Turkey Tuition Fee Scholarship (%100) Graduation GPA: 3.77 / 4.00 Graduation Rank: 4th.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, Bilkent University, Turkey

Sep 2015 - Aug 2021

- CS 353: Database Systems
- CS 281: Computers and Data Organization
- CS 101: Algorithms and Programming I
- CS 113: Introduction to Programming for Engineers

Computer Engineer, IBEX Information Technologies, Turkey

Apr 2018 - Dec 2018

- Smart Construction e-Procurement Platform
- Centralized Nursing System for the Old at Home
- Mobile Evaluation and Therapy Tools for Kids with Cerebral Palsy

Co-founder, IBEX Information Technologies, Turkey

Dec 2014 - Oct 2015

• I co-founded a company being selected in a national contest as a worthwhile project to be fully funded by an official call named 1512 Start-up Program by TUBITAK (The Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey).

Intern, Microsoft Summer School

Summer 2011

- Took lectures of Microsoft technologies to develop web-based and mobile applications using .NET platform.
- Developed a windows phone application.

Intern. Turk Telekom Inc.

Summer 2010

Application Development Department, Turkey

• Designed an internal database application.

PUBLICATIONS

- A. Usta, O. Ulusoy. SQL Query Recommendation Using Graph Neural Networks (on preparation 2022)
- A. Usta, A. Karakayali, O. Ulusoy. Explainable Natural Language Interface to Databases Using Keyword Mappings and Schema Graph (on submission 2022)
- A. Usta, I. S. Altingovde, R. Ozcan, O. Ulusoy. Learning to Rank for Educational Search Engines for K12 Students (on revision (minor), IEEE Transactions on Learning Technologies, TLT'21)
- A. Usta, A. Karakayali, O. Ulusoy. DBTagger: Multi-Task Learning for Keyword Mapping in NLIDBs Using Bi-Directional Recurrent Neural Networks. *International Conference on Very Large Data Bases* (PVLDB'21)
- A. Usta, I. S. Altingovde, R. Ozcan, O. Ulusoy. Re-finding Behaviour in Educational Search (International Conference on Theory and Practice of Digital Libraries (TPDL'19), Oslo, Norway)
- F. Basik, B. Hättasch, A. Ilkhechi, A. Usta, S. Ramaswamy, P. Utama, N. Weir, C. Binnig, U. Cetintemel. DBPal: A Learned NL-Interface for Databases, (Proceedings of the 2018 International Conference on Management of Data (SIGMOD'18), Gold Coast, QLD, Australia, July 2018)
- A. Usta, I. S. Altingovde, I. B. Vidinli, R. Ozcan, O. Ulusoy. How k-12 students search for learning? analysis of an educational search engine log, (37th Annual International ACM SIGIR Conference on Research and Development in Information Retrieval (SIGIR'14), Houston, TX, USA, June 2014)

SUPERVISION

Research Project Team Leader, Bilkent University

Feb 2019 - Aug 2021

- Graduate Students
 - 1. MS Student Akifhan Karakayali works on applying information retrieval paradigms to rank candidate translations of natural language queries to SQL in NLIDBs as his master thesis.
 - 2. MS Student *Mousa Farshkar* works on generating natural language text constrained on particular keywords present in a relational database.

- Undergraduate Students
 - 1. UG Students Akin Parkan, Busra Buyukgebiz, Ozan Aydin work on graph embedding techniques in graphs extracted from relational databases for the problems of query recommendation and outlier analysis.

ACADEMIC SERVICE

External Reviewer

- \bullet ACM Web Conference 2022
- \bullet IEEE TKDE 2021

PROJECTS

• Isim Sehir Game for Android Smart Phones (downloaded 50.000 times)	2015
• 3D Scanner, supported by TUBITAK under 1512 (start-up) program.	2014
• Coffee Fortune Teller For Android Smart Phones (as senior thesis for BSc)	2012
HONORS AND AWARDS	

H

• Most Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award Bilkent University, Ankara, Turkey	2021
• Huawei Ph.D Fellowship Bilkent University, Ankara, Turkey	2019-2021
• Most Outstanding Teaching Assistant Award Bilkent University, Ankara, Turkey	2018
• Nokia Honor Award IP Contest'12 Isik University, Istanbul, Turkey	2012
• High Honor Student Bilkent University Computer Engineering Department	2007-2012
• Stipend Scholarship Recipient Bilkent University Computer Engineering Department	2007-2012
• Success Rating: 1051st. OSYM University Entrance Exam (among 1.5 million students)	2007
• Graduation Rank: 3rd. Isparta Science High School	2007
• Graduation Rank: 1st. Primary School	2003